<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.10.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-10-02T00:04:41+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Alex T’s Blog</title><subtitle>A place for me to dump stuff that I find interesting. No guarantees that anyone else will think the same.</subtitle><author><name>Alex Torrens</name></author><entry><title type="html">Custom Maps on Garmin Devices</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/tips,/sports,/tech/2025/10/01/garmin-tips.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Custom Maps on Garmin Devices" /><published>2025-10-01T22:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-10-01T22:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/tips,/sports,/tech/2025/10/01/garmin-tips</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/tips,/sports,/tech/2025/10/01/garmin-tips.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="steps-to-get-custom-maps-on-garmin-wearables">Steps to get custom maps on Garmin wearables</h1>

<p>Need more maps on your Garmin wearable that aren’t already installed? Look no further! This guide will help you locate, download and transfer new maps that work in the exact same way as the preinstalled ones. All on-device courses and navigation should work the exact same. This how-to was heavily inspired by <a href="https://www.dcrainmaker.com/2019/08/installing-garmin-forerunner.html">DC Rainmaker’s great guide</a> on this, but a lot can change in that time, and a lot of new Garmin watches have been announced! So I took the liberty of updating the instructions. (I did email Ray to see if he wanted to reproduce this on his site to get to a wider audience, but no word back yet!)</p>

<p><strong>Tested with:</strong> Garmin Fenix 6 Pro Solar, Garmin Fenix 7 Pro Solar</p>

<p><strong>My setup:</strong> Macbook Pro M1 running MacOS Sequoia 15.3.2, Chrome Browser. I am located in the UK so my device came with European maps preinstalled.</p>

<p><em>This was first written in early 2025. I then updated the guidance in August 2025, to take into account changes for my newer Fenix watche. Keep reading below!</em></p>

<h2 id="steps-here">Steps here</h2>

<ol>
  <li>Navigate to <a href="https://garmin.bbbike.org/">https://garmin.bbbike.org/</a></li>
  <li>Choose your desired area by choosing on the map or searching.</li>
  <li>
    <p>Choose the format to be Garmin Openfietsmap Lite (Latin 1), and add your email address to receive the extract. Click Extract.</p>

    <p><img src="/assets/images/garmin-tips/fig1.png" alt="Choosing the target area in bbbike.org." /></p>

    <p><img src="/assets/images/garmin-tips/fig2.png" alt="Confirmation that your extract is being processed (and option to donate!)" /></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>You should receive an email like the following:</p>

    <p><img src="/assets/images/garmin-tips/fig3.png" alt="Email with link to extract in .zip format.)" /></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Download the zip from the email. Extract the zip, and isolate the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">gmapsupp-*.img</code> file. This is the disk image of the maps. Rename it so you can distinguish it from any others. I’d recommend the region you’ve chosen :)</p>

    <p><img src="/assets/images/garmin-tips/fig4.png" alt="Double-clicking on the .zip file gives the folder with the same name, where the maps are located." /></p>

    <p><img src="/assets/images/garmin-tips/fig5.png" alt="Contents of the uncompressed directory, including the all-important .img file." /></p>
  </li>
  <li>(For Mac) Download <a href="https://github.com/ganeshrvel/openmtp">OpenMTP</a> from github. This will be how you add the file to your garmin system.</li>
  <li>Open OpenMTP, and connect your watch to your computer with the cable.</li>
  <li>
    <p>Open the downloaded <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.img</code> file on one side, and Root &gt; GARMIN on the other side. <em>[Edit August 2025 when testing with Garmin Fenix 7 Pro]:</em> There are many reasons why OpenMTP may not recognise your device. <a href="https://github.com/ganeshrvel/openmtp/issues/276">Read about the issues linked on the github page.</a> What worked for me was ensuring that Garmin Express–which can be used to transfer <strong>official</strong> Garmin maps and updates–was completely closed, and not running in the background (Activity Monitor) on my Mac. Then, when restarting OpenMTP, my watch was recognised.
 <img src="/assets/images/garmin-tips/fig6.png" alt="UI of OpenMTP. You can see the pre-existing map images on the RHS, already stored on the device." /></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>You should be able to easily move the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.img</code> across, by dragging and dropping. Depending on the size of the file, it may take some time.</p>

    <p><img src="/assets/images/garmin-tips/fig7.png" alt="Transfer process of .img map file from computer to device" /></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>When you disconnect the watch, it will say ‘Loading Maps…’</p>

    <p><img src="/assets/images/garmin-tips/fig8.jpg" alt="Behaviour of watch immediately disconnecting from the computer" /></p>
  </li>
  <li>Done! The map should just load and function as expected when you navigate within the area you defined.</li>
</ol>

<p>This is a trail in Yosemite National Park, California, as an example.
<img src="/assets/images/garmin-tips/fig9.jpg" alt="Examples of how a GPX Route (created in Strava) appears using the new map" />
<img src="/assets/images/garmin-tips/fig10.jpg" alt="Examples of how a GPX Route (created in Strava) appears using the new map" />
<img src="/assets/images/garmin-tips/fig11.jpg" alt="Examples of how a GPX Route (created in Strava) appears using the new map" /></p>

<h2 id="update-august-2025">Update August 2025</h2>

<p>I lost my Fenix 6 Pro (I will tell the story elsewhere), and so when I received my Fenix 7 Pro I went through the same procedure to download some extra maps. What I discovered is that many more maps are available for free from Garmin for the 7 Pro series compared to the 6.
For the 6, typically the region you bought the device in was free (e.g. Europe for Europe, US for US etc.) and you had to pay for others (or download open source versions as above). However, for the 7, you get the option to download more for free. You can use <a href="https://www.garmin.com/en-XD/software/express/">Garmin Express</a> to do this. You can see the list of regions I can add below. Note that some cover less than a single country, some cover just one country, and some cover whole subcontinental or continental regions! 
Most are self-explanatory except for:</p>
<ul>
  <li>China ML - China Mainland</li>
  <li>SGMYVNPH - Singapore, Malaysia, Vietnam, Philippines</li>
  <li>THID - Thailand and Indonesia
You can download these via the watch (when charging and connecting to WiFi) but it’s quicker to do via the computer and <a href="https://www.garmin.com/en-XD/software/express/">Garmin Express</a>. This is probably also the quickest way to get updates, including the pre-installed ski and golf maps.
There are some notable exceptions, like India. I actually have a trip to India upcoming so I started to look for a non-Garmin version. This led me to the <a href="https://garmin.opentopomap.org/">https://garmin.opentopomap.org/</a> website. This, in effect, can replace steps 1-4 above. You choose your region, and download the ZIP straight away. It tells you the download size, and gives you the option to add contour lines (I haven’t tested this yet). You can then extract the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.img</code> from the zip and add to the watch via OpenMTP as before. Word of Caution: The watch can only connect to one programme at a time. For OpenMTP to correctly find and display the watch, you need to fully quit Garmin Express and stop any background activities. OpenMTP is a free open source app, implying there’s no obligation for the author(s) to fix any issues, but <a href="https://github.com/ganeshrvel/openmtp/issues/276">best-effort advice for troubleshooting is described on GitHub</a>.</li>
</ul>

<p>Once I’d downloaded the India region above, and copied it to the device, you can verify that it had transferred correctly by checking in the watch’s maps settings (Settings &gt; Map &gt; Map Manager). Your new map should be in the list.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/garmin-tips/fig12.jpg" alt="New map info on the watch" />
<img src="/assets/images/garmin-tips/fig13.jpg" alt="Example of the new map when viewing a premade course." />
<img src="/assets/images/garmin-tips/fig14.png" alt="Mapping options available from Garmin Express 1/2" />
<img src="/assets/images/garmin-tips/fig15.png" alt="Mapping options available from Garmin Express 2/2" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Alex Torrens</name></author><category term="tips," /><category term="sports," /><category term="tech" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Steps to get custom maps on Garmin wearables]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Llms</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/06/19/llms.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Llms" /><published>2025-06-19T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-06-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/06/19/llms</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/06/19/llms.html"><![CDATA[<hr />
<p>layout: default # Or a specific ‘post’ layout if you create one
title: “Language Models and AI: June 2025 Edit”
date: 2025-05-31 19:00:00 +0100 # Optional: time and timezone
categories: thoughts # Optional: categorise your post</p>

<h1 id="language-models-and-ai-june-2025-edit">Language models and AI: June 2025 Edit</h1>

<p>Let me start by saying I am not a massive fan of the term AI. It used to be an okay abbreviation for the scientific discipline of Artificial Intelligence—indeed, a previous director of mine has a PhD in AI from thirty years ago—but now it’s evolved to become a vague buzzword that doesn’t actually mean much.
AI is also not some future end goal or state… there are many applications and implementations of AI already out there in use. Content recommendation algoriths may be the most used version to the general person, however “AI” is finding uses in weather prediction, process optimisation, drug discovery and medical diagnoses.
And then, of course, there’s ChatGPT.
ChatGPT is an example of a <strong>Large Language Model (LLM)</strong>. Since ChatGPT—and its creator, OpenAI—were the first to release such an impressive chatbot with widescale adoption, it remains the most popular product and application of AI ever. The name ChatGPT may almost be at risk at being genericised! Whilst they became the first to mass-market, they are not the only player in this space. Google’s Gemini (my personal tool of choice), Anthropic’s Claude, XAI’s Grok, and myriad others are now out there and possible to use.
You will have noticed that these have been integrated <em>everywhere</em>… in all the enterprise tools I use at work, WhatsApp, even Google Search itself. It’s a bit overkill, if you ask me. But I don’t see this trend slowing down anytime soon. AI is the flavour of the decade so far, just like Blockchain and Quantum Computing before it.</p>

<h2 id="what-is-a-language-model">What is a Language Model?</h2>
<p>In essence, an LLM is a word predction machine. You feed it a sample of text, and it will predict and <strong>G</strong>enerate the most likely next word in the chain. <em>How</em> it does this is incredibly complex and computationally intensive, requiring the <strong>p</strong>retraining of hundreds of billions of parameters, working in 120-dimensional space and multiplying together <em>massive</em> matrices in objects called <strong>T</strong>ransformers. (That’s the <strong>GPT</strong> in ChatGPT, by the way.) This process is out of scope here, but I strongly encourage you to check our 3Blue1Brown’s <a href="https://www.3blue1brown.com/topics/neural-networks">amazing series</a> on deep learning, neural networks and language models. Grant’s work is some of the most high quality on the internet in my opinion, and it’s all free. He has even open-sourced his own <a href="https://github.com/ManimCommunity/manim">animation engine</a> for the visuals. Something I want to play around with more in the future…</p>

<h2 id="how-do-i-use-llms">How do <em>I</em> use LLMs?</h2>
<p>Let me start by stating that I am not an expert, nor a power user of these models. I do pay for Gemini Pro, which is less that £20 per month, which gets me access to Gemini 2.5 Pro, which as of writing is top of most <a href="https://lmarena.ai/leaderboard">leaderboards</a> for general-purpose LLMs. I have personally hitched my wagon to the the Google horse given their immense resources, legacy of AI research, and integration with the other Google services I frequently use. That’s not to say that it’s currently the best for everything, but it’s a great general purpose model for someone who cannot justify paying for multiple AI subscriptions.
Again, there is so much I’ve not really experimented with… Fully AI software development (“Vibe Coding”), image and video generation (more on that below), and AI agents and workflows.
However, I do use Gemini on an almost daily basis, for a myriad of tasks in my personal and professional life. <strong><em>Note of caution:</em></strong> my company has provided us enterprise licenses of Gemini, meaning our chats are not saved and used to further train the models. The same cannot be said for most free/personal versions of these models so I caution you sharing highly personal and/or confidential information.
An exception to this warning to this is models that you locally host and run, and therefore can be completely disconnected from the internet. However, given the sheer size and resources required to run the largest models, this is not available to most people. I will talk more about this below.
In my work and personal life, I find LLMs incredible useful for summarisations, translations, image-to-text descriptions, developing questions/topics where I’m out of the loop, coding help, legal text interpretation, cross-referencing documents, finding snyonyms, rhymes and alliterations for captions, and ELI5s. I’m sure there’s some things that I’ve missed out here.</p>

<p>Some of the things people have built using these models is AMAZING, and I believe these models are here to stay and will become a commodity. I don’t think you need to learn how they work deep-down, but for desk-based “knowledge” jobs, knowing when to use them is going to be <strong>critical</strong>. I personally think they will not replace a massive amount of jobs <em>yet</em>, but they can certainly increse productivity and output.</p>

<h2 id="open-source-ai-models">Open Source AI Models</h2>
<p>Most of the models commonly talked about are commercial, proprietary or closed-source. This means that a private company has created these, have perhaps commercialised them, and don’t want to share too much <a href="https://arstechnica.com/ai/2025/04/deepmind-is-holding-back-release-of-ai-research-to-give-google-an-edge/">special sauce</a> with others.
However—much like with traditional software applications—there is a thriving community of open source and source-available language models which can be viewed, modified and downloaded for personal (and even commercial) use.
<a href="https://huggingface.co/">HuggingFace</a> has become the platform of choice for open source machine learning models. There, you can explore, interact with, and test drive models before downloading and running them.
I personally have only tried downloading one LLM for use locally: a small version of Meta’s <a href="https://www.llama.com/">LLAMA</a> 3.1 model, using <a href="https://ollama.com/">Ollama</a>. Even this was 4 GB, and performs not too bad given its size and the laptop that I’m running it on. I initially experimented with it to allow me to enter more personal and confidential information (since the models runs locally, not connected to the internet and is not hosted by some company).
As I was writing this section, I decided to download DeepSeek’s 8B parameter “thinking” model (~5.5 GB)—again using Ollama—and wow this is impressive. Lots more experimentation to do this, but DeepSeek’s work is genuinely impressive.
Earlier in 2025, Chinese AI startup <a href="https://www.deepseek.com/en">DeepSeek</a> made some serious waves in the LLM world with their R1 reasoning model which performs almost on-par with the leading commercial western models. Why the hype? This model is <em>drastically</em> less resource intensive and is open source with an <em>incredibly permissive</em> MIT license (read: you can basically do whatever you want with it, for whatever purpose, including commercial).
Now, there are genuine concerns that have been raised over the filtering and training of a chinese-developed model—censorship perhaps front of mind to most—however this does not appear to be a problem in my downloaded “distilled” version.
It’s genuinely exciting to me to see widely-available, open source LLMs go toe-to-toe with commercial ones from tech giants. Who knows how the future in this space will unfold.</p>
<h2 id="on-image-and-video-generation">On image and video generation</h2>

<h2 id="environmental-concerns">Environmental concerns</h2>]]></content><author><name>Alex Torrens</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[layout: default # Or a specific ‘post’ layout if you create one title: “Language Models and AI: June 2025 Edit” date: 2025-05-31 19:00:00 +0100 # Optional: time and timezone categories: thoughts # Optional: categorise your post]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Half a decade as a Herbivore: In hinsight</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/life/2025/05/12/half-decade-herbivore.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Half a decade as a Herbivore: In hinsight" /><published>2025-05-12T19:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-05-12T19:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/life/2025/05/12/half-decade-herbivore</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/life/2025/05/12/half-decade-herbivore.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="half-a-decade-as-a-herbivore-in-hinsight">Half a decade as a Herbivore: In hinsight</h1>

<p>Let’s get it out of the way: As of 14 April 2020, I have been vegan for five years. There was no cold tofurkey moment on that, indeed I could be a day or two out, but this is probably the earliest day that I consciously know I consumed zero animal products.</p>

<h2 id="what-happened-to-dusty-bin-the-boy-who-ate-everything">What happened to “Dusty Bin”, the boy who ate everything?</h2>

<p>Dusty Bin was a <del>prestigious</del> prize awarded annually by my <em>Cubs</em> group, basically Scouts for younger kids. I believe I won it on a camp, where I’m guessing I couldn’t and wouldn’t stop eating anything put in front of me.
There is precedence; ask my parents and they will tell you that I’ve been a big eater my entire life. I just love food (I Still do, don’t worry). I’m more of a savoury person than a sweet person–given the choice, I’d always choose a starter over pudding–but this all started to change in 2019.
I was working in London, in the office five days a week (who remembers that?!), trying to eat relatively healthy (read: not buy lunch out every day) and simultaneously not go bankrupt. Thank god I lived three minutes from a Lidl in my first London houseshare!
At the same time, this was around the time Greta Thunberg was becoming world-famous, and the environmental issues surrounding meat consmption were coming on my radar. For a long time, I dismissed them, thinking that “meat is essential”, and “well of course meat is murder, how else do you make it”. I was blissfully ignorant to the Animal rights issues–I just flat-out refused to watch the viral factory farm facebook video of the week.
I don’t remember what made the first switch flip, but I suddenly decided that I had to make <em>some</em> change to my eating habits. So, I started eating pescatarian–only excluding the flesh of land animals–four days a week. I figured I liked meat too much and didn’t want to remove it from my diet fully. I carried on like this, mostly eating “pesci” Monday to Thursday, then eating what I wanted on the “fun” days of the week, for a few months. Typically there would be some fish, but I also started exploring the meat alternatives that were available in late 2019. At the same time, I started learning more and more about the other issues with meat, and felt the uncomfortable impending “scope creep” of my lifestyle.
The next watershed moment was on a packed train, heading home for Christmas. I’d heard about this film (I’m wary to call it a documentary–more on that later) on Netflix called <em>The Game Changers</em>; a look at how it’s not just possible to <em>survive</em> on a plant-based diet, but <em>thrive</em> and excel athletically. I think this was the first time I truly realised that humans didn’t need <strong>any</strong> animal products, at least in the modern era in a developed country (both of which apply to me). A second switch had flipped in my brain. I politely refused the meat dish served at home that Christimas Eve evening, and quitely debated with myself what on <em>earth</em> I was going to do about dinner the following day. In reality, I just couldn’t resit myself on Christmas Day, but I am pleased to say that was the last time I consciously ate meat in the UK.
“That’s quite the qualifier there, Alex, so you did eat meat after then?” you may be thinking. You are of course right to point this out. I did eat chicken meat during two work trips to Nigeria in February and March 2020. I justified it to myself as being in a very different culture, on a business trip, and needing one less thing to worry about.
Back to the UK. On Boxing day, 2019, I told myself no meat today. So I didn’t eat meat. Nor the day after, or the day after that. I made it to New Year’s Eve, at a dinner party, and still managed to avoid it. I’d now done a week, with no real drama and so didn’t stop. I hadn’t started labelling myself as a vegetarian or anything, I was just telling people that I’m temporarily not eating meat. It helped that as the calendar rolled over to 2020, Veganuary started in the UK. This is an amazing charity who manage to get hundreds of thousands to sign up each year and see if they can last a month with no animal products. Luckily, all the supermarkets and eating establishments have cottoned on to this and use January as a great opportunity to release new plant-based products. This made my entry to the world of meat-free eating very easy. Yay for capitalism!
You may also have realised that my big shift to meat-free eating was, surprisingly, not dominating the headlines in early 2020. What started out as reports of many critical flu cases in an unfamiliar city in China turned into the (still ongoing) COVID pandemic which ruled all of our lives for a couple of years. I moved back to my parents’ just before Lockdown 1 in the UK, probably a wise move to get out of my shoebox flat in Hoxton, but it made the eating arrangements a little tricky now there was a veggie in the house.
As we started to live through yet another major historical event–a trend I’m getting a little sick of now–I started reading more about plant-based diets, animal agriculture, zoonotic diseases and antibacterial resistance (no clue why on the last two). Eventually, the evidence got so overwhelming I was really struggling to accept that I was stumbling down the path to a lifestyle with zero animal products. I’d already swapped cow milk for oat; that was easy. I had no real intention of cutting out cheese. But the more I read, the more I watched, the more I realised I the moral conclusion of my experiments so far was veganism.</p>

<p>[joe rogan game changers podcasts]</p>

<p>Vegetarianism is pretty common in the UK, especially amongst students and young professionals in cities. I’d go as far as to say that it’s pretty normal; no one bats an eye if you go for a veggie option. Most people stop there and don’t go any further. I got to this point, realised that I thought I was “half-arsing” the whole thing. After all, who drew the artitrary line that meat is BAD and dairy is GOOD? (if you don’t think animals die as a result of the dairy industry, that’s exactly what farmers want you to think) and realised I should go either 0% or 100% instead of 50%. And I couldn’t morally go back to eating meat… so there I was, on 14 April give or take, and here I am now, five years later, not planning any deviation any time soon.</p>

<h2 id="how-has-it-been">How has it been?</h2>

<p>For the massive majority, I have done really well in the previous five years. I still find it awkward sometimes to tell people that I’m vegan, and contrary to the popular stereotype I totally avoid the topic until it’s absolutely necessary, like at dinner time.
Unfortunately the word vegan has a lot of misconceptions, and I find that people automatically sort vegans into one of two complete opppsite ends of the spectrum: Either the super fit, healthy, ‘body is a temple’ type <strong>or</strong> dishevelled, malnourished, protein-deficient, anaemic weaklings. I do chuckle at this, because which is it supposed to be?! I’d like to think I’m closer to the former on the spectrum. Indeed, anecdotally I’ve been in the best physical shape of my life during this five year period. I ran two marathons on back-to-back weekends in 2022 (maybe story for a future post), smashed my goals in a Half Ironman race in 2024, and never trained at the same intensities or frequencies before. Sure, I’m not going to be winning any bodybuilding competitions any time soon, but that’s not my goal. Would these have still happened if I didn’t change my diet? Probably. In fact, almost certainly. But hopefully it goes to show that athletic performance is definitely possible. Scrap that, don’t look to me for this advice! Ask Lewis Hamilton, Novak Djokovic and Serena Williams and see how they are getting on.
I still have to justify or defend my position and lifestyle a fair amount. I guess I should encourage it to some extend, if people can’t critique in an inquisitive and respectful way, <em>and</em> understand the science and logic, then we can have a really interesting conversation. After all, I was once in their shoes as the non-vegan who thought it was crazy!
I think–or at least want to believe– that most people are don’t want to inflict suffering on animals. At the same time, they don’t want to destroy the planet they live on. Most reasonable* people are in favour of laws, regulations and movements that work to mitigate these problems. But that’s until the topic of meat comes up. There’s something so ingrained and cultural about meat that it can be very hard to get people to change their minds. Again, I was one of these people, so I can’t judge too much. But times are changing. People are becoming more understanding and accepting of new ways of life. Cities like London, Berlin and Brighton have become vegan paradises. There’s a long way to go, but we’ve made a lot of progress. Even france now has some plant-based bakeries and patisseries!
As perferences change, so do the products available on supermarket shelves and on restaurant menus. There are now a whole host of different companies selling vegan alternatives to family favourites like sausages, yogurt, milk, bacon, and now even steaks. There has been a noticable slowdown since the boom a couple of years back–some ranges have reduced and, unfortunately, some companies haven’t survived–but it’s amazing to see so many options available. Maybe a future blog post will detail my favourite brands and items, and the tech behind them.
What we have on shelves these days are plant-based (or funghi) alternatives. There are two other flavours of vegan products that are coming to a store near you soon©: Fermentation and Cultured. The former relies on growing microbes which produce proteins and other molecules that we can use in foods–yum–and the latter is what’s more popularly referred to as lab-grown meat. I don’t think many people realise that this tech actually exists outside of labs and is actually on plates (and in dog bowls)… Singapore became the first country in the world to approve the sale of cultured chicken in restaurants, and as of early 2025 cultured dog food is now available in the UK. I am so excited for this technology–regardless of whether I end up consuming it or not–that I have started investing in this tech where I can. There’s not many opportunities for the non-millionaire retail investor, except for the UK-based fund <a href="https://www.agronomics.im/">Agronomics</a>, which you can buy shares in publically. Of course do you own research, this is not investment advice. 
I just say to this to say that whilst the vegan fad may be over, and the hype died down, there is still research and investment towards an <em>animal exploitation-free</em> world, but not necessarily a <em>meat-free</em> world.</p>

<p>So, to summarise, yes I call myself vegan, yes I’m still alive after five years, and no I’m not planning on stopping any time soon. Even if I move to France. If you have other questions, see my (slightly tongue-in-cheek) Q&amp;A below.</p>

<h2 id="q--a">Q &amp; A</h2>
<ul>
  <li>What do you miss the most?
When asked this in real life, I usually quip that when you learn where it all comes from, you lose your appetite for it. But in reality, the answer is probably Sunday roast lamb with all the trimmings (of course with a Yorkshire pudding), or proper greasy seaside fish and chips (authentic chippy chips are still a vice of mine), or even just having available options everywhere.</li>
  <li>Come on, is it <strong>really</strong> healthy for you? 
I’m not the guy to ask on this.
Here are some reputable sources on this:
<a href="https://www.nhs.uk/live-well/eat-well/how-to-eat-a-balanced-diet/the-vegan-diet/">NHS</a>
<a href="https://www.bda.uk.com/resource/vegetarian-vegan-plant-based-diet.html">British Dietetic Association</a>
<a href="https://www.pcrm.org/">Physician’s Committee for Reponsible Medicine (USA)</a>
<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/27886704/">Academy of Nutrition and Dietetics (USA)</a>
You will note in the sources above that key words are “appropriately planned”. This can lead people to assume that a healthy vegan diet is actually really hard. My counter to this is “shouldn’t all diets be carefully-planned?” Look at the state of health across the UK! Obesity is everywhere in the developed world. All diets should be planned \rant</li>
  <li>Honey??
If it’s a product of animal exploitation, then it’s not vegan. Having said that, many people calling themselves vegan do eat honey, and it’s certainly less bad than some other animal products. Given the option, I wouldn’t <em>choose</em> it, but to be honest, I don’t look out for it as much on ingredient lists as I do with other animal products.
“But you’re directly supporting bees! And we need bees” Sounds like a convincing argument, certainly what I thought in the past, until you learn that honey bees are so good at taking pollen, they actually out-compete all the other bee species which actually pollinate other plants. [find source]</li>
  <li>B12??
B12 is an interesting one, because despite it definitely not being produced by plants, it’s also not products by animals (directly, at least). B12 is made by bacteria that live in the soil, that we used to eat tonnes of when we grew our own food at ate it still somwaht dirty. Modern food processing has virtually entirely removed this source of B12, and the same thing is happening with the food that your food (i.e. farm animals) eats. This means that it’s possible to buy B12 supplements for animal feed. Which leads to the question… what’s more efficient? Taking a supplement yourself, or taking it via an inefficient middle-man?</li>
  <li>Alcohol??
Alcohol can be hard to find sources on, especally wine, with all of its thousands of labels and vineyards. <a href="https://www.barnivore.com/">Barnivore</a> is a useful resource, and more and more products in the UK have vegan labels on. But again, I will be honest, I am not the most diligent at checking whether the pint I’ve just ordered is vegan or not. There are (figuratively, hopefully not literally) bigger fish to fry</li>
  <li>What about clothing? Medicine?
Medicine is easy. I am totally morally justified in taking any medicine I need as prescribed or recommended. And I encourage anyone to do the same, of course including vaccines. Animal testing is slowly becoming obsolete and ethically dubious. There may be some animal products used in the production of medicines–for example, the flu vaccine is grown in chicken eggs–but again, <a href="https://www.vegansociety.com/go-vegan/definition-veganism">“as far as is practical”</a>
Clothing is a little trickier. As veganism is a lifetyle that eschews all animal products, this does also cover wool, leather, fur and down.
I am disclosing here that I have knowingly and deliberately bought three products of animal origin in the past five years: A tailored wool coat in Vietnam, a wool skiing thermal base layer, and <em>second hand</em> leather boots.
I will probably also purchase wool suits in the future; synthetic or other natural wool alternatives just aren’t there yet, and I buy suits so infrequently I can justify this to myself. As for buying leather second hand, one can make arguments for all sides of that debate and it’s not one I am going to wade into here. One thing that is universally great is that fur is becoming shunned more and more by consumers and the luxury fashion houses.
Popular shoe brands are doing great things with plant-based leathers these days, made out of all sorts of other materials, check them out!</li>
  <li>You must make some exceptions, right?
Other than what is covered in the other answers above, I make two other important concessions or exceptions. The first is cross contamination. Whilst it may be yucky and cause a health hazard for raw ingredients, I generally don’t have an issue if my food is cooked on the same grills, in the same oil, using the same itensils as meat products. Since it’s not an allergy issue for me, I elect to make my life and that of others around me simpler. It also allows more food providers to offer more options, if they are going for the “plant-based” label and not the “100% vegan” which would reqire everything to be separate.
The second is to loosen the rules ever so slightly when travelling. I will still not consciously order any animal products, and anything labelled vegan is obviously where I start, but in some countries it’s just not going to be possible or practical to 100% ensure a vegan option. After all, I have to eat <em>something!</em> Two examples come to mind: fish sauce in Thailand and ghee in India. These ingredients are near-ubiqutous in their respective countries, and enquiring to every local or street food vendor whether the tofu pad thai or lentil dhal are totally compliant is just not going to be practical or possible in every circumstance. So, I do what I can where I can.</li>
  <li>Underrated perk? 
Having a kitchen free of contamination! No separating chopping boards, washing my hands 10 times whilst cooking a meal, no raw meat going off in the fridge. I am also yet to get food poisoning since adopting this diet, though I know I’m definitely jinxing it.</li>
  <li>Worst thing?
Being able to get a meal or snack anywhere in the world :( Some countries are great for options, but others are really lacking. Portugal was very hard for me, outside the cities. Unfortately the same is still true in France, something I may want to live in the future.
And, I know it’s a little cringe, but seeing all the animals out in the fields in the UK–which many would say is a lovely site–when you know why they are there, and how much land of our island <em>which was originally entirely forest</em> is being dedicated to exploiting then.</li>
  <li>Why do you still support places that still sell meat?
Frankly I have no choice. Am I going to stop going out with friends just because they’re not going to a vegan restaurant? Or my local tesco? Again, it’s not practical. However, what I try and remember is that all these for-profit corporations are in the business of <em>making money</em> first and foremost. How they do that, is secondary. So, purchasing vegan products, creating the demand, informing their future purchasing decisions and strategy, is something I can get behind. This is why I have to morally allow myself to purchase products from <a href="https://vivera.com/news/">JBS</a>, one of the world’s largest meat companies with a horrifying presence in the Amazon region (yes, they’ve read the tea leaves, diversified and are now invested in some plant-based products)</li>
  <li>Recommendations of recipes, creators, media and restaurants?
Coming soon!
As immediate help, Happy Cow for restaurants, BOSH! for recipes, but honestly google and youtube (and probably TikTok too) are your friends here. Maybe when I get a place of my own I will finally also get in on the vegan food content game, with a food science spin.</li>
  <li>What would you do on a desert island yadda yadda yadda?</li>
  <li>Why do you eat such unhealthy, ultra-processed fake meat?
Erm, cos it tastes nice? Next. But seriously, very few people choose this lifestyle because they hate the taste of meat. So what’s wrong with replicating the tastes, textures and sensations that I still enjoy, but in cruelty-free way? As for them being ultra-processed, well a) some are obviously worse than others and b) have you <em>seen</em> how they make pig sausages and bacon??</li>
  <li>Vegan cheese is oily crap, no?
Mostly, yes, they lack any nutrition at all so I usually avoid them. However, there are some amazing artisanal cheeses out there, made of nuts and traditional cheesemaking techniques, but due to economies of scale and lack of subsidies they are of course more expensive than their dairy counterparts. I have bought a Christmas cheeseboard a couple of times from <a href="https://lafauxmagerie.com/">La Fauxmagerie</a> in London which I can highly recommend (as with their cheese nights!)</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Alex Torrens</name></author><category term="life" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Half a decade as a Herbivore: In hinsight]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Trip Report: Three Valleys Skiing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/thoughts/2025/05/12/trip-report-skiing-2025.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trip Report: Three Valleys Skiing" /><published>2025-05-12T19:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-05-12T19:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/thoughts/2025/05/12/trip-report-skiing-2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/thoughts/2025/05/12/trip-report-skiing-2025.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="trip-report-three-valleys-skiing">Trip Report: Three Valleys Skiing</h1>
<h3 id="trip-dates-01-09-february-2025">Trip Dates: 01-09 February 2025</h3>
<h3 id="location-the-three-valleys-savoie-france">Location: The Three Valleys, Savoie, France</h3>
<p>I love skiing. I am very lucky to have been a few times with my parents whilst growing up, and most years since having a job, which have led to me being relatively competent despite the fact I’m UK-based and ski for–at most–six days a year.
This trip was going to six of us lads heading to <a href="https://www.les3vallees.com/en">Les Trois Vallées</a>–marketed as the largest connected ski area in the world–where my friend Xav’s stepdad happens to have a chalet. But calling this place a chalet was like calling Buckingham Palace a starter home. This place is ridiculous, with <strong>five</strong> ensuite rooms, modern kitchen, two garages, and a (communal) gym and two games rooms. Perhaps the most surprising thing about it is that it doesn’t have a hot tub!</p>

<p>The flight to Lyon was smooth. We picked up our hire cars and immediately started noticing heavier than usual traffic on the roads leading to the mountains. When we got to Albertville, to do The Big Shop, we started receiving snippets of concerning information. There had been a rockfall on the one road leading up to the ski resorts with no diversion possible. Single point of failure, anyone? One car had been hit (no serious injuries thankfully), and there were now very large chunks taken out of the road’s surface. Cars were backed up on the motorway for dozens of kilometres. We decided to wait it out in a car park in Albertville to start with, and see what new information came out. When nothing groundbreaking emerged, we eventually loaded up with more snacks and decided to brave it through the night to see if we got anywhere. During the first three hours, we barely made it <strong>one kilometre</strong>. It got to midnight, and again we’d not even managed to get out of town back on the main road.
Whilst we were idling along with tens of thousands of others (it was holiday transition day too) the French authorities had worked miracles and set up a bi-directional system in the unaffected tunnel leading away from the mountain. This meant that <em>some</em> cars could trickle up and down from the resorts. But it was slow. Very slow. It was maybe 1am when we finally merged back onto the main road, the RN90. We were taking shifts driving and sleeping. Having manual cars was not fun at all. But we <em>were</em> moving forward; I guess once the down-mountain traffic had calmed, they’d started letting traffic flow in both directions in the tunnel simultaneously. We were all taken by surprise when we eventually got to the tunnel, and through, and into the quiet sleeping town of Moutieres. We’d made it! We zoomed up the mountain, to the village of St Martin de Belleville. By the time I’d showered–a necessity after our ordeal–and got into bed, it was 6am.
At one point on that mad saturday, we’d all started to wonder that the trip may be over before it started. None of us would have put money on us skiing the next day. But you better belive that we kitted up, handed over some crazy money to the hire shop, and hit the slopes. Sure, it was a short session, and probably not worth the EUR 70 lift pass, but we were skiing. The overpriced 25cl Carlsberg on the mountain tasted extra good that afternoon.
The rest of the trip went pretty successfully in comparison. After Xav–who’s spent his entire life on skis–I was the next most experienced. When Xav went off to do a day of touring, I was in charge of guiding a day on the slopes with the others, which proved popular. I was skiing well, practicing different types of turns, a little off-piste here and there. Xav offered to take me to do a couple of his backcountry routes from earlier in the week, which scared me but also intrigued me. I’ve never ski-toured before! Back to Sport 2000 Hire it was, to swap out my on-piste skis for all-mountain skis (a nice pair of 95mm Dynastars) and an avalanche pack.
The half-day was amazing. Hard, and exhausting, but wow. I feel like this is what skiing really should be. <em>Lifts? Where we went, we didn’t need lifts.</em> (Ignore the first one up to Pont de la Masse.) Hiking with the skis on my back was a completely new experience, and made the descent all the more satisfying. Did I mention I can’t really ski in deep powder? Lots of room for improvement on that. In normal alpine skiing–where the chairlifts do all the hard work–I’m never out of breath and rarely leave heart rate zone 1. This was different though. Ski hiking is sweaty work, especially in all the layers. I was constantly dressing and undressing.
There was a very conveniently placed <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/7h524RG5G5LpTGC56">refuge</a> for lunch, which <em>even</em> had a delicious vegan main (hard to come by in France 🙁). We re-hydrated with beer and water, and then rejoined the piste to find the others.
No other big stories to tell… fun evenings in the chalet, with pairs taking it in turns cooking, playing poker with wine corks as chips. We chilled (and sweated) at the new posh spa in the village. A glass of wine or two. Watched England beat France in the 6 Nations. All good fun.
Our final day was Sunday 9 February, circled on my calendar as Super Bowl Sunday. This was going to be a 24 hour day. Here’s a summary of that Sunday:
Wake up at 05:30 CET to drive to Lyon Airport, fly to Gatwick, get the train to Calum’s in Elephant and Castle, collect my bags that I’d left there, get the tube to Euston, catch the train to Milton Keynes, get picked up by Alim and Xav (who’d driven from Gatwick), get to Xav’s, have dinner with his parents, and then wait for the Superbowl to start at 11:30 GMT. I survived just about to the end, which was at about 4am. How fun. And, of course, I was working the following day. No rest for the wicked (and no PTO for the traveller).</p>

<p>I say this after every ski trip, but it’s <em>finally</em> time for me to invest in some kit of my own. To start: boots and helmet. Any excuse to buy more sport kit.</p>]]></content><author><name>Alex Torrens</name></author><category term="thoughts" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Trip Report: Three Valleys Skiing Trip Dates: 01-09 February 2025 Location: The Three Valleys, Savoie, France I love skiing. I am very lucky to have been a few times with my parents whilst growing up, and most years since having a job, which have led to me being relatively competent despite the fact I’m UK-based and ski for–at most–six days a year. This trip was going to six of us lads heading to Les Trois Vallées–marketed as the largest connected ski area in the world–where my friend Xav’s stepdad happens to have a chalet. But calling this place a chalet was like calling Buckingham Palace a starter home. This place is ridiculous, with five ensuite rooms, modern kitchen, two garages, and a (communal) gym and two games rooms. Perhaps the most surprising thing about it is that it doesn’t have a hot tub!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hello, world!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/meta/2025/05/11/my-first-jekyll-post.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hello, world!" /><published>2025-05-11T19:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-05-11T19:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/meta/2025/05/11/my-first-jekyll-post</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/meta/2025/05/11/my-first-jekyll-post.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="hello-world-jekyll-style">Hello world, Jekyll style!</h1>

<p>This is my first micro-post using Jekyll. It’s pretty exciting.</p>

<p>I have always thought about hosting my own microblog. I don’t want to make money, I just want to share some stuff that I find interesting.
I researched for the lowest barrier to entry to this world–ideally with the lowest cost–and settled on a combination of <a href="https://pages.github.com/">GitHub pages</a> and <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll</a>. Amazingly, this is FREE to use, if you are happy to keep a generic URL reponame.github.io. However, I recently decided to purchase alextorrens.com (I definitely didn’t need the .com domain but, eh, it’s my name) and I linked the repo to my custom domain and BAM, here we are.
Expect to see this “static” blog website change a fair bit, as a slowly add content and learn how to make it prettier. Lots of tech I’m revisiting and/or learning from scratch:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Git in the terminal and GitHub</li>
  <li>Jekyll (OSS project written in Ruby and the Gems ecosystem)</li>
  <li>Websites and domain names</li>
  <li><a href="https://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/">Markdown</a></li>
  <li>Who knows what else when I run into one of many technical issues!</li>
</ul>

<p>Some of the topics I may want to write about include:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Sport–both playing and watching</li>
  <li>Tech</li>
  <li>Food</li>
  <li>Cooking</li>
  <li>Photography</li>
  <li>Travel</li>
  <li>Science
And combinations thereof!</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Alex Torrens</name></author><category term="meta" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hello world, Jekyll style!]]></summary></entry></feed>